<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" 
     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" 
     xmlns:eg="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
     xmlns:egXML="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
     xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" 
     xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:lang="en" n="tei_clarin">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CLARIN.SI TEI schema for language corpora</title>
        <author>Tomaž Erjavec, tomaz.erjavec@ijs.si</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>CLARIN.SI</publisher>
        <date>2021-10-31</date>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>This file is freely available and you are hereby authorised to copy, modify, and redistribute it in any way without further reference or permissions.</p>
        </availability>
        <pubPlace>
          <ref target="https://github.com/clarinsi/TEI-schema">https://github.com/clarinsi/TEI-schema</ref>
        </pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Made from scratch.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>Slovenian Research Infrastructure for Language Resources and Tools <ref target="http://www-clarin.si/">CLARIN.SI</ref>.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2021-10-31">Tomaž Erjavec: change example document a lot.</change>
      <change when="2021-09-29">Tomaž Erjavec: reduce to corpora, work on text.</change>
      <change when="2021-08-24">Tomaž Erjavec: start adding text of recommendations.</change>
      <change when="2020-12-16">Tomaž Erjavec: change representation of whitespace.</change>
      <change when="2019-09-06">Tomaž Erjavec: added module for figures, so we can code tables; newly generated schemas.</change>
      <change when="2018-12-31">Tomaž Erjavec: added module for names and dates so we can code e.g. parliamentary corpora; newly generated schemas.</change>
      <change when="2018-12-28">Tomaž Erjavec: added module for spoken text so we can code e.g. parliamentary corpora; newly generated schemas.</change>
      <change when="2018-10-10">Tomaž Erjavec: added transcription module so we can use facsimile; newly generated schemas.</change>
      <change when="2018-04-09">Tomaž Erjavec: added dictionaries module and newly generated schemas as TEI has changed (added @msd et al).</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main"><ref target="https://github.com/clarinsi/TEI-schema/">CLARIN.SI TEI schema for language corpora</ref></titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <docDate>2021-10-31</docDate>
        <docEdition>0.3</docEdition>
      </titlePage>
      <p></p>
      <divGen type="toc"/>
    </front>
    
    <body>
      <div xml:id="sec-intro">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>This document gives recommendations on the preferred
	<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">TEI</ref>
	XML encoding of langauge
        corpora in the <ref target="https://www.clarin.si/">CLARIN.SI</ref> repository.</p>
	
	<p>The TEI customisation for CLARIN.SI supports the encoding of language corpora and makes
	explicit recommendations on the manner of encoding various phenomena.</p>

	<p>These recommendations are written as a TEI ODD document (= proze recommendations
	and formal schema), on the basis of which it is possible to derive an XML schema
	expressed either as a RelaxNG schema, a DTD or a W3C schema, and such schemas are
	also part of this Git repository.</p>

        <p>When using these recommendations, the following points should be taken in consideration:
        <list>

          <item>The TEI Guidelines are a large and complex set of specifications, and the
          CLARIN.SI recommendations do not attempt to give an introduction to them. Rather,
          it concentrates only on aspects of the Guidelines that are most likely to be of use
          in encoding linguistically annotated language corpora which are likely to be deposited in
	  the CLARIN.SI repository.</item>
          
          <item>It is difficult if not impossible to determine in advance what kinds of corpora
          and their mark-up will be deposited in the repository. While we tried to cater for the
          more obvious encoding needs, it is possible that new users will have to use TEI elements
          or attributes that are not mentioned here.</item>

          <item>Since these recommendations are (always) work in progress, we have left the formal
          specification (i.e. the XML schema) very unconstrained, so it can accommodate encoding
          practices that we have not (yet) foreseen. The downside of this is that the XML schemas
          will allow constructs that are at odds to those that we propose in the prose of the
          recommendations. Therefore, the prose should be taken as the definitive way of encoding
          the phenomena under discussion, i.e. even if a corpus validates against the
          schema, it might still not be encoded according to these recommendations.</item>

          <item>In the text of these recommendations, every mention of an element is linked to its
          definition, where examples of use are also given. The text also makes frequent reference
          to the text of the TEI Guidelines. However, the TEI Guidelines give generic examples and
          explanations, which can be at odds with particular recommendations that are made here, so
          the ones from the TEI Guidelines should be taken with a grain of salt.</item>

        </list>
        </p>
        
        <p>The rest of these recommendations are structured as follows:
        <list>
          <item>the rest of this section details the <ref target="#sec-scope">scope and
          purpose</ref> of the recommendations;</item>

          <item><ref target="#sec-general">Section 2</ref> gives the general requirements that
          a CLARIN.SI corpus has to meet;</item>

          <item><ref target="#sec-overall">Section 3</ref> explains the overall document
          structure of a CLARIN.SI corpus;</item>

          <item><ref target="#sec-metadata">Section 4</ref> concentrates on encoding the corpus
	  metadata;</item>
          
          <!--item><ref target="#sec-transcript">Section 5</ref> gives the encoding of the corpus body;</item-->

          <item><ref target="#sec-linguistic">Section 6</ref> details linguistic annotations;</item>

          <item><ref target="#sec-multimedia">Section 7</ref> gives information on multimedia information;</item>

          <item><ref target="#sec-conversion">Section 9</ref> discusses conversions to and from
          the CLARIN.SI format;</item>

          <item><ref target="#examplar">Appendix A</ref> gives a complete example document that illustrates
          the encoding according to the CLARIN.SI schema.</item>

          <item><ref target="#schema">Appendix B</ref> gives the formal specification of
          the CLARIN.SI schema.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
        
      <div xml:id="sec-scope">
          <head>Scope and purpose</head>
          <p>These recommendations consists of readable guidelines and a formal TEI ODD schema with
          derived XML schemas in various schema languages.  They are intended for the encoding of
          linguistically annotated corpora, regardless of the language or country of origin, for
          the purposes of scholarly investigations, be they from the field of linguistics,
          political science, history or other humanities and social sciences disciplines.</p>
          
          <p>In developing a schema for structuring data, two approaches can be adopted: a
          descriptive one, where as much as possible of the original data distinctions are kept in
          the target encoding; or a prescriptive one, where the target encoding is severely
          constrained, to enable seamless data interchange and esp. interoperability with software
          tools. These recommendations adopt the <emph>descriptive</emph> approach, as the source
          data, time and effort devoted to converting it, the intended applications will differ
          considerably, and it is likely that any prescriptive schema would soon turn out to be too
          restrictive. Nevertheless, the recommendations do try to limit the plethora of encoding
          options otherwise available in TEI to those that could be sensibly applied to language
          corpora, and where more than one option is available in TEI to encode a given phenomenon,
          the schema and especially the text guidelines attempt to recommend only one option.</p>
        </div>
        
    </div>
      
    <div xml:id="sec-general">
      <head>General requirements</head>
      
      <p>A CLARIN.SI corpus should, in general, capture as much of the text from the source as
      possible, while the presence of graphical items or other elements that could not or were not
      transcribed should be indicated by markup, in particular with the use of <gi>gap</gi>.</p>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-chars">
          <head>Characters</head>
          
          <p>The corpus should be encoded in Unicode, using the UTF-8 character encoding, at least
          for European languages.  In cases where the original contains characters from the Unicode
          Private Use Area, these should be given their closest Unicode equivalents.<note>TEI
          supports preserving the original Private Use Area codepoints by using the <gi>g</gi>
          element, the use of which is further explained in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/WD.html">Characters, Glyphs,
          and Writing Modes</ref> of the TEI Guidelines. However, such characters will rarely if
          ever be used in corpora, so the current proposal does not include the gaiji module which
          allows the use of this element - if they are needed, then the CLARIN.SI ODD needs to
          be changed.</note></p>
          
          <p>End-of-line hyphens can be removed, and the split words joined in order to simplify
          linguistic processing. It is recommended that this practice is documented in the TEI
          header of the corpus, in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> element.</p>
          
          <p>The following characters, esp. prevalent when the source documents are in Word or
          HTML, deserve special mention:
          
          <list>
            <item>NO-BREAK SPACE (U+00A0) prevents, with some applications, an automatic line break
            at its position and collapsing consecutive white space characters into a single
            space. As this recommendation is not interested in preserving the details of the
            layout, and the use of this character complicates (or breaks) further processing
            esp. lingistic annotation, it is recommended that this character is substituted by the
            normal space character (U+0020). The same holds for other variants of spaces (U+2000 -
            U+200A), which are, however, used much less frequently.</item>
            
            <item>NON-BREAKING HYPHEN (U+2011), similarly to NO-BREAK SPACE, prevents a
            line break, in this case, following its position. With a smiliar reasoning
	    as above, it is recommended that this character is substituted by the normal
	    hyphen character ('-', U+002D).</item>
            
            <item>SOFT HYPHEN (U+00AD) indicates that a word can be hyphenated at that
            point. Occurences of this character should be removed from the corpus,
            because, again, they only complicate or break further processing.</item>
          </list>
          </p>
          
          <p>While not required, it is sensible to also normalise sequences of whitespace
          characters (such as tabulators, end-of-line characters and spaces) into a single
          space or end-of-line character. Again, this simplifies further (esp. linguistic)
          processing.</p>
          
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-document">
          <head>Documenting the encoding process</head>
          
          <p>Difficult encoding situations that are not covered by the TEI Guidelines can be
          documented in the <gi>editorialDecl</gi> of the corpus TEI header.  In particular, if the
          source texts has been changed (so, omitting or normalising figures, text, EOL hyphens,
          quotes, special characters, etc. as discussed above) this practice can be documented in
          the <gi>correction</gi>, <gi>normalization</gi>, <gi>quotation</gi>, and, as mentioned,
          in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> element of the editorial declaration. Two further elements,
          namely <gi>segmentation</gi> and <gi>interpretation</gi> can also be used to document
          these aspects of the encoding process. The example below illustrates the use of these
          elements:

          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-editorial">
            <editorialDecl>
              <correction>
                <p>Found typos in the source have been silently corrected.</p>
              </correction>
              <normalization>
                <p>Tables have been omitted from the corpus. Spacing has been normalised
                to single space. Soft hyphens have been removed.</p>
              </normalization>
              <hyphenation>
                <p>End-of-line hyphens have been silently removed.</p>
              </hyphenation>
              <quotation>
                <p>Quotation marks have been left in the text and are not explicitly
                marked up.</p>
              </quotation>
              <segmentation>
                <p>The texts are segmented into paragraphs, sentences, words and
                punctuation.</p>
              </segmentation>
              <interpretation>
                <p>Word-level linguistic annotation comprises the lemma of a word and its
                morphosyntactic description, which follow the
                <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/">MULTEXT-East morphosyntactic
                specification Version 6</ref> for Slovene.</p>
              </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
          </egXML>
          </p>

          <p>When automatic procedures have been used to encode the texts (most prominently, to
          add linguistic markup, as discussed in the Section on <ref
          target="#sec-linguistic">Linguistic annotation</ref>) this should be documented in
          the <gi>appInfo</gi> element of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, as shown in the example
          below:

          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-appinfo">
            <appInfo>
              <application version="1.0" ident="reldi-tagger">
               <label>ReLDI morphosyntactic tagger and lemmatiser</label>
               <desc>MSD tagging and lemmatisation performed with ReLDI Tagger trained for
               Slovene and available from
               <ref target="https://github.com/clarinsi/reldi-tagger">GitHub</ref>.</desc>
              </application>
            </appInfo>
          </egXML>
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-langs">
          <head>Languages</head>
          <p>The language of an element's text content is in TEI, as in XML, signaled by the
          value of its <att>xml:lang</att> attribute.  The CLARIN.SI recommendations require
          that each element that contains text is either marked by this attribute, or one of
          its ancestors is; in particular, the root element of the corpus should have an
          <att>xml:lang</att> attribute. For multilingual documents (excluding cases where only
          a minor part of the text is in another language), the language code of the root
          element should be <q>mul</q> for <q>multiple languages</q>. Note that if, going by
          the ancestor axis, the values of two <att>xml:lang</att> are in conflict, the one
          closer to the context node is relevant one.
          </p>
          
          <p>The values of <att>xml:lang</att> should follow <ref
          target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/bcp47">BCP 47</ref>, cf. also <q><ref
          target="https://www.w3.org/International/questions/qa-when-xmllang">xml:lang in XML
          document schemas</ref></q>.</p>
          
          <p>It is good practice to document the languages used in the <gi>langUsage</gi>
          element of the TEI header.</p>
          
          <p>Apart from the above considerations, a related question is where to draw the line
          between the object and meta languages, i.e. the language of the corpus and the
          language of the mark-up. The TEI defines the names of the elements and attributes in
          English, and the language of the corpus will, of course, depend on the country of the
          parliament. It is less straightforward to decide in which language the attribute
          values (such as the values of the <att>type</att> attribute) should be. CLARIN.SI
          recommends that these should also be in English.</p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-idents">
          <head>Identifiers and referencing</head>
          <p>In order to simply refer to elements of a TEI document (i.e. a CLARIN.SI
          corpus), elements can be marked with an ID, i.e. given the <att>xml:id</att> attribute
          with a unique value, obeying certain format requirements as defined by
          <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">W3C</ref>.</p>
          
          <p>CLARIN.SI requires an <att>xml:id</att> attribute on the root element of each corpus
          file, which should, furthermore, be identical to the filename (modulo the file
          extension).  CLARIN.SI also recommends that the divisions of the document (element
          <gi>div</gi>), if any, should also be given identifiers. While any element can be given
          an <att>xml:id</att>, this is in general, not a good idea; rather, only those elements
          that will or could be referenced should be marked with this attribute.</p>
          
          <p>TEI offers a number of attributes that contain (URI) pointers.  Where the reference
          is to an element inside the document, the value of the <att>xml:id</att> being
          referred to should be preceded by a hash (#), as mandated by the XML standard. If the
          ID pointed to is from another document, then the full URI needs to be used.</p>

	  <p>However, as such URIs can be very long, TEI also offers another way of pointing, which
	  can be used to shorten such long URIs, and this is defined by the <gi>prefixDef</gi>
	  element in the TEI header, as illustrated below:

	  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-prefixDef">
            <prefixDef ident="mte" matchPattern="(.+)" 
                       replacementPattern="http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/tables/msd-fslib-sl.xml#$1">
              <p xml:lang="en">Private URIs with this prefix point to feature-structure elements defining the Slovenian MULTEXT-East Version 6 MSDs.</p>
            </prefixDef>
          </egXML>

	  With such a definition, we can use the much shorter pointers in the mark-up of words,
	  such as <val>mte:Pd-nsg</val>, which are then, via a regular expression mapping in the
	  prefix definition converted to the full URI <val>http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/tables/msd-fslib-sl.xml#Pd-nsg</val>.
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-temporal">
          <head>Temporal information</head>
          <p>Corpora cancontain time-related information, e.g. the date and time of a tweet, the
          birth (and death) dates of an author, etc. In general, such information in TEI is stored in the
          attributes of the pertinent element, which take as their values a date and possibly time,
          according to the ISO 8601 Date and Time Formats, and specified in the <ref
          target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second
          Edition</ref>. TEI offers a very rich set of attributes and ancillary elements to specify
          time-related information, which are discussed in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONADA">Dates and
          Times</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</p>

          <p>CLARIN.SI corpora can use any of the TEI temporal attributes and elements, however,
          for most purposes, the following five attributes will suffice:
          <list>
            <item><att>when</att>: when a certain event happened;</item>
            <item><att>from</att>, <att>to</att>: the start and end of an event or state;</item>
            <item><att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>: the earliest and latest known
            time that an event or state took place, used in cases where the exact time
            is not known.</item>
          </list>
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-files">
          <head>Files</head>
          <p>While this recommendations make the assumption that a complete corpus is one TEI XML
          document, this does not mean that it also has to be stored in one file, as the file
          structure is distinct from the concept of XML documents. To enable one XML document to be
          composed of many files, the <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xinclude/">XInclude</ref>
          mechanism should be used. Typically, a corpus will then be composed of a file containing
          the root XML element <gi>teiCorpus</gi>, which contains the corpus header, while
          individual <gi>TEI</gi>-rooted text files will be included in the corpus using the
          <gi>include</gi> element from the XInclude namespace, as illustrated by the following
          example:

          <eg xml:id="exa-xinclude">
            <![CDATA[<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="Sk-11/SI-1990-05-07-01.xml"/>]]>
          </eg>
          </p>
          
          <p>As mentioned, we recommend that the file has the same name as the value of the
          <att>xml:id</att> attribute of the root element of the file. This e.g. guarantees
          that each file of the corpus has a unique name.</p>
        </div>
        
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-overall">
        <head>Overall document structure</head>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-corpstruct">
          <head>Corpus structure</head>

          <p>As illustrated below, a CLARIN.SI corpus is rooted in a <gi>teiCorpus</gi>
          element. The <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus contains the metadata for the complete
          corpus, including the metadata that is marked with the <att>xml:id</att> attribute and
          referred to by the subordinate <gi>TEI</gi> elements, such as the defined taxonomies for
	  text types.</p>
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-docstructure">
            <teiCorpus xml:lang="xx">
              <teiHeader>
                <!-- Common corpus metadata -->
              </teiHeader>
              <TEI xml:id="id.1">
                <teiHeader>
                  <!-- Document metadata -->
                </teiHeader>
                <text>
                  <body>
                    <!-- Document text -->
                  </body>
                </text>
              </TEI>
              <!-- More TEI elements here -->
            </teiCorpus>
          </egXML>

          <p>An individual <gi>TEI</gi> element is referred to as a <hi>corpus element</hi>.  In
          cases where such a category is simply defined (e.g. a corpus of books) it contains one
          text from the corpus, however, if corpus "texts" are very short (tweets, samples) or
          very long or complex (encyclopedias) one corpus element can contain a collection or
          part of a "text" according to some well-specified criterion.</p>

          <p>In cases of smaller corpora, the top level <gi>teiCorpus</gi> can also be omitted,
          so the complete corpus is rooted simply in a <gi>TEI</gi> element, and the individual (short)
	  texts are encoded as <gi>div</gi> elements.</p>
          
          <p>The <gi>text</gi> element can, in general, apart from the obligatory <gi>body</gi>,
          also contain front matter in <gi>front</gi> and back matter in <gi>back</gi>.
	  However, front and back are seldomly used in computer corpora.</p>
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-textstructure">
            <TEI xml:id="id_1">
              <teiHeader>
                <!-- Document metadata -->
              </teiHeader>
              <text>
                <front>
                  <!-- Front matter -->
                </front>
                <body>
                  <!-- Transcription text -->
                </body>
                <back>
                  <!-- Back matter -->
                </back>
              </text>
            </TEI>
          </egXML>

        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-textstruct">
          <head>Text divisions</head>
          
          <p>The <gi>div</gi> elemet can be used to further divide the texts.
	  The divisions can be nested, as shown in the example below:
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-divsimple">
            <body>
              <div>
                <head>Part I.</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div>
                <head>Chapter 1</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div>
                <head>Chapter 2</head>
                ...
              </div>
              ...
            </body>
          </egXML>
          As with corpus elements, there is no hard and fast rule what should constitute a
          division, except that they typically have a heading.

	  The divisions can be further characterised by their <att>type</att> and, possibly,
	  <att>subtype</att> attributes. They can be used when the digital source of the texts
	  either explicitly (e.g. via its structure, as in up-conversion from Word documents) or
	  implicitly (e.g. via pattern matching the content of the headings) indicates what kind of
	  a division it is. For example:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-divtype">
            <body>
              <div type="part">
                <head>Part I.</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div type="chapter">
                <head>Chapter 1</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div type="chapter">
                <head>Chapter 2</head>
                ...
              </div>
              ...
            </body>
          </egXML>
          </p>
          
          <p>If used, the values of the <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes will
          depend on the structure of the source texts, on the need to distinguish the types of
          divisions, as well as on the ability to automatically recognise them or the available
          effort to manually add them. The CLARIN.SI specification does therefore not enforce the
          use of these attributes nor does it restrict their values.  Below we give an example of a
          relatively complex structure made on the basis of a corpus of parliamentary proceedings:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-divakn">
            <body>
              <div type="prayers">
                <head>Prayers</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div type="oralStatements">
                <head>Speaker’s Statement</head>
                ...
              </div>
              <div type="questions">
                <head>Oral Answers to Questions</head>
                <div type="debateSection" subtype="topic">
                  <head>Health</head>
                  <div type="debateSection" subtype="askedPerson">
                    <head>The Secretary of State was asked—</head>
                    <div type="debateSection" subtype="questionAnswer">
                      <head>Ambulance Waiting Times</head>
                      ...
                    </div>
                  </div>
                </div>
              </div>
              <div type="pointOfOrder">
                <head>Points of Order</head>
                ...
              </div>
            </body>
          </egXML>
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-docvariants">
          <head>Document variants</head>
          <p>Copora can exist in two or more versions, e.g. the original and its translation(s) into
          another language(s).</p>

          <p>TEI offers a number of options on how to encode <q>variant</q> texts, most of them
          discussed in the <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.htm">Chapter on Linking,
          Segmentation, and Alignment</ref>. We here present the simplest option, where it is
          assumed that the text of each language exists in a separate TEI document and that the
          senteces should be aligned between the original and translation. As shown in the
          example below, which gives one sentence from the file <code>text-orig.xml</code> and one
          from the file <code>text-trans.xml</code> it is in this case enough to specify the
          <att>xml:id</att> on both elements and use the <att>corresp</att> attribute to point to
          the aligned sentence(s):

          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-variants">
            <!-- From text-orig.xml: -->
            <s xml:id="orig.1" corresp="text-trans#trans.1">Ali je to slaba stvar?</s>

            <!-- From text-trans.xml: -->
            <s xml:id="trans.1" corresp="text-orig.xml#orig.1">キレるってそんなに悪いことでしょうか？</s>
          </egXML>
          It should be noted that the relation between the aligned elements does not need
          to be 1-1: if the relation is 0-1 or 1-0, then the non-aligned element is simply
          not given in a <att>corresp</att>; if the relation is n-1 or 1-n, then several
          IDs are given as values of the <att>corresp</att> attribute,
          e.g. <code>corresp="text-orig.xml#orig.3 text-orig.xml#orig.4"</code>.</p>
        </div>
        
      </div>

      <div xml:id="sec-metadata">
        <head>Corpus metadata</head>
        <p>TEI allows significant metadata to be added to a document.  The metadata is
        contained in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, which in corpora can appear at two
        levels:
        <list>
          <item>the overall corpus teiHeader, i.e. as part of the <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element;</item>
          <item>the teiHeader of individual corpus texts, i.e. as part of a <gi>TEI</gi> element.</item>
        </list>
        It is recommended that the metadata that is common to the whole corpus is stored in
        the corpus TEI header, whereas the text-specific metadata is in the corpus text TEI
        header.</p>
        
        <p>It is outside the scope of this specification to give all the details of a
        <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, for this, the user is referred to the Section on the <ref
        target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html">TEI header</ref>
        of the TEI Guidelines, and, of course, to the example corpora that are part of the
        CLARIN.SI Git repository. Here we do, however, give some examples that are useful for
	a variety of corpora.</p>

        <div xml:id="sec-speakers">
          <head>Speaker metadata</head>
          <p>Speech corpora typically contain information about speakers, which is given in the
          corpus TEI header, in particular in the <gi>listPerson</gi> element, itself a part of the
          participant description, i.e. the <gi>particDesc</gi> element.</p>

          <p>A <gi>listPerson</gi> typically contains <gi>person</gi> elements, which give
          information on an individual person, as the example below illustrates.
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-speakers">
            <person xml:id="KucanMilan1941">
              <persName>
                <surname>Kučan</surname>
                <forename>Milan</forename>
              </persName>
              <sex value="M">male</sex>
              <birth when="1941-01-14">
                <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3197229">Križevci</placeName>
              </birth>
            </person>
          </egXML>

          Each <gi>person</gi> must have an <att>xml:id</att> attribute, so that it can be referred
          to from the transcription. Apart from that, the only required element is
          <gi>persName</gi>, giving the name of the person. This can be contained directly in the
          element, or, as the preferred option, further decomposed into the person surname(s) and
          forename(s) or even other elements, as explained in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDPER">Personal
          Names</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</p>

          <p>As illustrated above, further person metadata can contain the sex of the person and
          their birth date and place. Other potentially useful elements are the persons
          <gi>death</gi> date and place, as well as (possibly time stamped) <gi>education</gi>,
          <gi>occupation</gi>, and <gi>affiliation</gi>.</p>

          <p>Persons can have further attributes, and TEI offers various elements (typically typed)
          to express them; they are introduced in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDPERSEpc">Personal
          Characteristics</ref> of the TEI Guidelines. The two more general ones are
          <gi>state</gi>, which contains the description of some status or quality attributed to a
          person (or organization), often at some specific time or for a specific date range and
          <gi>trait</gi>, which differs from <gi>state</gi> that it is independent of the volition
          or action of the holder and usually not at some specific time or for a specific date
          range. The former could, for example, be used to encode the fact that a person was jailed
          for a given period of time, while the latter would e.g. be used for the information that
          a person is handicapped.</p>

          <p>It can be advantageous to refer to external knowledge sources about a person, such as
          Wikipedia or VIAF. This is encoded using the <gi>idno</gi> element, whose content is
          typically an URI, while the <att>type</att> attribute denotes the kind of knowledge
          source referred to.
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-external">
            <person xml:id="Kucan_Milan1941">
              <persName>
                <surname>Kučan</surname>
                <forename>Milan</forename>
              </persName>
              <idno type="wikimedia" xml:lang="sl">https://sl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Ku%C4%8Dan</idno>
              <idno type="wikimedia" xml:lang="en">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Ku%C4%8Dan</idno>
              <idno type="viaf">https://viaf.org/viaf/68121580/</idno>
            </person>
          </egXML>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      
      <!--div xml:id="sec-transcript">
        <head>Encoding of texts</head>
	<p>In this section we illustrate the encoding of various types of texts from corpora in the
	CLARIN.SI repository.
	
	<p>
	  <bibl>Erjavec, Tomaž; et al., 2021, Multilingual comparable corpora of parliamentary
	  debates ParlaMint 2.1, Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI, <ref
	  target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1432">http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1432</ref>.
	  </bibl>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relations">
   <text ana="#reference">
      <body>
         <div type="debateSection">
            <head>REPUBLIKA SLOVENIJA DRŽAVNI ZBOR</head>
            <head type="session">1. izredna seja</head>
            <head type="chairman">Sejo sta vodila predsednik Državnega zbora dr. Milan Brglez in podpredsednik Janko Veber.</head>
            <note type="time">Seja se je začela ob 10. uri.</note>
            <note type="speaker">PREDSEDNIK DR. MILAN BRGLEZ:</note>
            <u who="#BrglezMilan"
               xml:id="ParlaMint-SI_2014-08-25-SDZ7-Izredna-01.u1"
               ana="#chair">
               <seg xml:id="ParlaMint-SI_2014-08-25-SDZ7-Izredna-01.seg1">Spoštovane kolegice poslanke in kolegi poslanci, gospe in gospodje!</seg>
               <seg xml:id="ParlaMint-SI_2014-08-25-SDZ7-Izredna-01.seg2">Začenjam 1. izredno sejo Državnega zbora, ki sem jo sklical na podlagi drugega odstavka 58. člena in drugega odstavka 60. člena Poslovnika Državnega zbora. Obveščen sem, da se današnje seje ne more udeležiti poslanec Marijan Pojbič. Vse prisotne lepo pozdravljam.</seg>
               <seg xml:id="ParlaMint-SI_2014-08-25-SDZ7-Izredna-01.seg3">Preden preidemo na določitev dnevnega reda seje, dovolite, da nagovorim Državni zbor v zvezi s spominom na žrtve vseh totalitarnih in avtoritarnih režimov.</seg>
	       ...
	    </u>
	 </div>
      </body>
   </text>
	  </egXML>
	</p>

	<p>
	  <bibl>Verdonik, Darinka; et al., 2021, Spoken corpus Gos VideoLectures 4.2
	  (transcription), Slovenian language resource repository CLARIN.SI,
	  <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1444">http://hdl.handle.net/11356/1444</ref>.</bibl>
	  <egXML>
	    
	  </egXML>
</p>
-->	
<!-- From ParlaMint:
        <p>The transcriptions of the parliamentary debates the central part of these
        recommendations and this section explains how to encode the transcriptions of speeches
        proper, the commentary inserted by the transcribers, and the encoding of interruption
        of speeches and various verbal and non-verbal incidents in the parliament. Most of
        these elements are explained in the Chapter on <ref
        target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TS.html">Transcription of
        Speech</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</p>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-uterrance">
          <head>Utterances and commentary</head>
          <p>In the transcriptions the main distinction to be made is between the
          transcriptions of the utterances of the speakers against the commentary inserted by
          the transcriber, such as the titles of the divisions, results of voting, comments on
          what is happening in the chamber etc. The former should be encoded using the
          utterance element, <gi>u</gi>, while latter are encoded using a variety of elements,
          such as <gi>head</gi> or <gi>note</gi>, and possibly others, as further discussed
          below. Below we give an example of a rather straightforward start of a division:
        
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-relations">
            <div>
              <head>REPUBLIKA SLOVENIJA DRŽAVNI ZBOR</head>
              <head type="session">nadaljevanje 39. seje</head>
              <note type="chairman">Sejo so vodili predsednik Državnega zbora dr. Milan Brglez
              in podpredsednika Primož Hainz ter Matjaž Nemec.</note>
              <note type="time">Seja se je začela ob 10.03.</note>
              <note type="speaker">PREDSEDNIK DR. MILAN BRGLEZ:</note>
              <u who="#SDZ7.BrglezMilan" ana="#chair">
                <seg xml:id="SDZ7-Redna-39-2018-03-27.seg1">Spoštovani kolegice poslanke in
                kolegi poslanci, gospe in gospodje!</seg>
                <seg xml:id="SDZ7-Redna-39-2018-03-27.seg2">Začenjam z nadaljevanjem 39. seje
                Državnega zbora.</seg>
                ...
              </u>
              ...
            </div>
          </egXML>
          
          The example starts with the division heading, saying that this is the National Assembly
          of the Republic of Slovenia, with the second heading specifying that this is the
          continuation of the 39th session. Next come three notes, first one specifying who
          chaired the session, the second when the session started and the third the name of the
          first speaker. It should be noted that these are not formal specifications, rather,
          they are simply parts of the transcript that have been wrapped in certain elements.</p>
          
          <p>After these preliminary notes comes the transcript of the speech proper, which, as
          mentioned, is encoded using the <gi>u</gi> element. Its main attribute is
          <att>who</att>, giving the pointer to the <gi>person</gi> element containing the
          metadata of the speaker. The <gi>u</gi> element can also have the <att>ana</att>
          attribute giving one or more pointers to a typology of types of speakers. In our case,
          it would point to a category that specifies that the speaker is the chair of the
          session.</p>
          
          <p>The utterances can (but are not required to) be segmented using the generic
          TEI element for segments, <gi>seg</gi>, encoding the paragraphs of the source
          transcription.<note>The reason why the TEI element for paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>) is not
          used is that utterances, being essentially (transcriptions of) spoken text, do not
          allow for internal paragraphs, a concept pertinent to written text.</note></p>
        </div>
        
      </div-->
      
      <div xml:id="sec-linguistic">
        <head>Linguistic annotation</head>
        <p>This section introduces common types of linguistic annotation that can be added language
        to the corporus texts; the examples should be sufficient for users to be able to add
        further types of linguistic annotation to their own corpora.</p>
        
        <p>The TEI Guidelines discuss basic linguistic annotation in their Chapter on <ref
        target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AI.html">Simple Analytic
        Mechanisms</ref> and we follow one particular option given there. In particular, it is
        recommended that (where possible) the annotation is in-line (as opposed to stand-off),
        i.e. that the linguistic annotation is given in the main document, and therefore mixed
        with the other annotations, rather than in a separate document with pointers into the
        base text.</p>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-anawords">
          <head>Basic word-level annotation</head>
          
          <p>Basic linguistic annotation comprises sentence segmentation, tokenisation,
          part-of-speech tagging and lemmatisation. The CLARIN.SI recommendations
          specialise the recommendations given in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AI.html#AILALW">Lightweight
          Linguistic Annotation</ref> of the TEI Guidelines. The following example shows the
          basic principles of the annotation:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-ud">
            <s>
              <w msd="UPosTag=DET|Case=Gen|Gender=Neut|Number=Sing|PronType=Dem" lemma="ta">Tega</w>
              <w msd="UPosTag=PRON|PronType=Prs|Reflex=Yes|Variant=Short" lemma="se">se</w>
              <w msd="UPosTag=PART" lemma="sploh">sploh</w>
              <w msd="UPosTag=AUX|Mood=Ind|Number=Sing|Person=1|Polarity=Neg|Tense=Pres|VerbForm=Fin" lemma="biti">nisem</w>
              <w msd="UPosTag=VERB|Aspect=Perf|Gender=Masc|Number=Sing|VerbForm=Part" lemma="zavesti" join="right">zavedel</w>
              <pc msd="UPosTag=PUNCT">.</pc>
            </s>
          </egXML>
          
          Sentences are marked up using the <gi>s</gi> element, words with the <gi>w</gi>
          element and punctuation symbols with the <gi>pc</gi> element. To retain the
          linguistically significant whitespace, the <att>join</att> element is used, with the
          possible values being <val>no</val> (assumed to be the default), <val>right</val>
          (no whitespace to the right of the token) and <val>left</val> (no whitespace to the
          left of the token) and <val>both</val> (no whitespace to either side of the
          token). While, in the preceding example, it would be more intuitive to have the
          value <val>left</val> marked on the full-stop, we recommend that only the value
          <val>right</val> is used on the preceding token, as this simplifies processing.</p>
          
          <p>The base form of a word is given in the <att>lemma</att> attribute,<note>Note
          that punctuation characters, <gi>pc</gi>, do not have a <att>lemma</att> attribute,
          as they cannot sensibly be said to have lemmas.</note> while the situation with the
          part-of-speech tags is somewhat more complicated. For analytic tagsets, where a
          "part-of-speech tag" is actually a set of attribute-values, as in the example above,
          the <att>msd</att> attribute should be used. For synthetic tagsets, such as the <ref
          target="https://www.ling.upenn.edu/courses/Fall_2003/ling001/penn_treebank_pos.html">Penn
          Treebank tagset</ref>, which have atomic tags that cannot always be decomposed into
          attribute-value pairs (e.g. "TO" for the word "to"), a better alternative is to use
          of the <att>pos</att> attribute.</p>

	  <p>There is also a third option, for tags that are look like strings, however, they
	  are meant as a shorthand for a feature-structure representation, as is the case with
	  the <ref target="http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/html/">MULTEXT-East tagset</ref>. For
	  these, it is best to use the generic <att>ana</att> attribute, whose value is a
	  pointer, as shown in the following example:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-msd">
            <s>
              <w ana="#Pd-nsg" lemma="ta">Tega</w>
              <w ana="#Px------y" lemma="se">se</w>
              <w ana="#Q" lemma="sploh">sploh</w>
              <w ana="#Va-r1s-y" lemma="biti">nisem</w>
              <w ana="#Vmep-sm" lemma="zavesti" join="right">zavedel</w>
              <pc ana="#Z">.</pc>
            </s>
          </egXML>
          
          Here, the tags are pointers to identifiers, where the elements bearing these
          identifiers define the appropriate feature-structures, i.e. pairs of
          attribute-values, as in the example below:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-fs">
            <fs xml:id="Pd-nsg" xml:lang="en">
              <f name="CATEGORY"><symbol value="Pronoun"/></f>
              <f name="Type"><symbol value="demonstrative"/></f>
              <f name="Gender"><symbol value="neuter"/></f>
              <f name="Number"><symbol value="singular"/></f>
              <f name="Case"><symbol value="genitive"/></f>
            </fs>
          </egXML>
          </p>

	  <p>Such feature structures are grouped together in the feature-value library
	  (<gi>fvLib</gi>) element, which can be contained in its own <gi>TEI</gi> element of
	  the corpus. As <att>ana</att> is a pointer, it can also contain complete URLs
	  (e.g. <code>http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/tables/msd-fslib2-sl.xml#Pd-nsg</code>) which
	  enables the feature-structure definitions to be stored externaly to the
	  corpus. However, prefixing such PoS tags for each token by the complete URL would
	  lead to very large files. This is why the TEI offers a mechanism to shorten 
	  references to URLs. This mechanism is explained in the Section <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SAPU">Using
	  Abbreviated Pointers</ref> of the TEI Guidelines, and we give below and example:
	  
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-prefix">
            <s>
              <w ana="mte:Pd-nsg" lemma="ta">Tega</w>
              <w ana="mte:Px------y" lemma="se">se</w>
              <w ana="mte:Q" lemma="sploh">sploh</w>
              <w ana="mte:Va-r1s-y" lemma="biti">nisem</w>
              <w ana="mte:Vmep-sm" lemma="zavesti" join="right">zavedel</w>
              <pc ana="mte:Z">.</pc>
            </s>
          </egXML>
	  
	  As can be seen, the only difference to the preceding example is that the values (IDs) of
	  the tags are preceded by <code>mte:</code> rather than <code>#</code>. This prefix should
	  be then expanded by the processing software to whatever the <gi>prefixDef</gi> element,
	  defined in the TEI header, specifies, as shown in the example below:
	  
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-prefixDef">
            <prefixDef ident="mte" 
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/msd/tables/msd-fslib-sl.xml#$1">
              <p xml:lang="en">Private MSD URIs with the prefix "mte" point to fs elements
              defining the Slovene MULTEXT-East Version 6 MSDs, cf. <ref
              target="http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/">http://nl.ijs.si/ME/V6/</ref> and <ref
              target="https://github.com/clarinsi/mte-msd">https://github.com/clarinsi/mte-msd</ref>.</p>
            </prefixDef>
          </egXML>
	  </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-ananorm">
          <head>Normalised and syntactic words</head>
          
          <p>In certain contexts a word (or, in general, a token) in the text needs to be
          normalised in a certain way. This can happen with historical
          texts, which contain archaic wordforms and where we wish to annotate them with
          their modernised forms, or when the text is linguisticaly annotated, and the
          annotation framework distinguishes original words form syntactic words (i.e. has the
          concept of <q>multiwords</q>), as is the case in the <ref
          target="https://universaldependencies.org/format.html#words-tokens-and-empty-nodes">Universal
          Dependencies framework</ref>.</p>
	  
	  <p>For simple normalisation, where one word token is normalised into another word token,
	  the <att>norm</att> attribute on word or punctuation tokens should be used, as explained
	  at the end of the Section <ref
	  target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/AI.html#AILALW">Lightweight
	  Linguistic Annotation</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</p>

	  <p>More challenging is the case where one original word token must be represented as
	  several normalised words, either in the context of historical corpora or, as mentioned
	  above, in the context of multiword units. For this we use embedded empty words with
	  associated <att>norm</att> attributes, and possibly other attributes with linguistic
	  annotation. For example, Czech has the word <q>abyste</q> which is decomposed into two
	  syntactic words, <q>aby</q> and <q>byste</q>. This should be encoded as in the following
	  example:<note>Note that the example is rendered in three lines, however, the correct
	  encoding in the corpus is actually in a single line, without any spaces between the
	  elements, as otherwise the new line and indenting spaces are actually a part of the word
	  <q>abyste</q>.</note>

          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-1-2">
	    <w>abyste<w norm="aby" lemma="aby"/><w norm="byste" lemma="být"/></w>
          </egXML>
	  </p>
	  
          <p>There are also cases where two (or more) original words correspond to one normalised
          word. Here, it is the outer word that carries the <att>norm</att> and possibly other
          linguistic attributes, while the inner words are the original ones. For example, Slovene
          used to form the superlative form of adjectives with the word <q>naj</q> written
          separately (and often as <q>nar</q>), while in contemporary Slovene the <q>naj</q> is a
          prefix of the adjective. This case should be encoded as follows:
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-2-1">
	    <w norm="najlepši" lemma="lep"><w>nar</w> <w>lepši</w></w>
          </egXML>
	  </p>
	</div>
	
        <div xml:id="sec-anasegment">
          <head>Segmental annotation</head>
          
          <p>A common annotation type, used e.g. for marking named entities or terms, is
          segmental annotation, where a stretch of text or tokens is simply enclosed in XML
          tags, as the following example illustrates:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-names">
            <s>
              <name type="person">
                <w>John</w>
                <w>Malkovič</w>
              </name>
              <w>went</w>
              <w>to</w>
              <name type="location">
                <w>New</w>
                <w>York</w>
              </name>
              <pc>.</pc>
            </s>
          </egXML>
          
          TEI offers a number of elements that can be used for such annotations,
          e.g.:
          <list>
            <item><gi>term</gi> for marking up terms, discussed in the Section on <ref
            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COHQU">Terms,
            Glosses, Equivalents, and Descriptions</ref> of the TEI Guidelines;</item>
            
            <item><gi>name</gi> for various types of names, or, the more general <gi>rs</gi>
            for <q>referring string</q>, e.g. <tag>rs type="person"</tag> her
            husband<tag>/rs</tag>, discussed in the Section on <ref
            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONARS">Referring
            Strings</ref> of the TEI Guidelines;</item>
            
            <item><gi>num</gi> for numbers and <gi>measure</gi>, usually comprising a number, a
            unit, and a commodity name (e.g. <tag>measure type="weight" quantity="5000"
            unit="ton" commodity="coal"</tag>five thousand tons of coal<tag>/measure</tag>,
            discussed in the Section on <ref
            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONANU">Numbers
            and Measures</ref> of the TEI Guidelines;</item>
            
            <item><gi>date</gi> and <gi>time</gi>, discussed in the Section on <ref
            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#CONADA">Dates
            and Times</ref> of the TEI Guidelines;</item>
            
            <item><gi>seg</gi> for cases where TEI does not have a specific element for some
            type of segmental markup, e.g. <tag>seg type="swearword"
            subtype="religious"</tag>Damn<tag>/seg</tag>; this element is discussed in the
            Section on <ref
            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SASE">Blocks,
            Segments, and Anchors</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</item>
          </list>
          
          It should be noted that for cases of discontinuity of the segment, the <att>prev</att>
          and <att>next</att> attributes can be used to link its parts together. Furthermore,
          the <att>part</att> attribute can be used to specify the type of the fragments, as
          shown in the following example:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-terms">
            <term xml:id="t1" part="I" next="#t3">di-</term> and
            <term xml:id="t2" part="I" next="#t3">poli</term><term xml:id="t3" part="F">methyl</term>
          </egXML>
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-analinking">
          <head>Linking annotation</head>
          
          <p>For analyses that establish relations between tokens or segments, such as syntactic
          dependency analysis or semantic role labelling, the <gi>linkGrp</gi> element, explained
          in the <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html">Chapter on
          Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment</ref> is used. It is composed of <gi>link</gi>
          elements, which give two or more references to IDs, as illustrated in the following
          example:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-analysis-syntax">
            <s xml:id="ssj1.1.5">
              <w xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t1">Tega</w>
              <w xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t2">se</w>
              <w xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t3">sploh</w>
              <w xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t4">nisem</w>
              <w join="right" xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t5">zavedel</w>
              <pc xml:id="ssj1.1.5.t6">.</pc>
              <linkGrp type="UD-SYN" targFunc="head argument">
                <link ana="ud-syn:obj" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t1"/>
                <link ana="ud-syn:expl" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t2"/>
                <link ana="ud-syn:advmod" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t3"/>
                <link ana="ud-syn:aux" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t4"/>
                <link ana="ud-syn:root" target="#ssj1.1.5 #ssj1.1.5.t5"/>
                <link ana="ud-syn:punct" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t6"/>
              </linkGrp>
              <linkGrp type="SRL" targFunc="head argument" corresp="#ssj1.1.5" >
                <link ana="srl:PAT" target="#ssj1.1.5.t5 #ssj1.1.5.t1"/>
              </linkGrp>
            </s>
          </egXML>
          
          In the example, each token, as well as the sentence element are given an ID, and the
          first link group specifies the Universal Dependencies syntactic analysis of the
          sentence, while the second one give its semantic role labels.  They are distinguished
          by their <att>type</att> attribute<note>We do not specify the values of
          <att>type</att> of the link gropu as the range of possibilities is too great and not
          known in advance.</note>, while the <att>targFunc</att> attribute explains the
          functions of the references given in the <att>target</att> attributes of the contained
          <gi>link</gi> elements.</p>
          
          <p>The contained links then give the references to the head and argument tokens of
          the relation, while the <att>ana</att> attribute specifies what kind of a relation
          this is. It should be noted that the value of the analysis attribute is a pointer,
          and, in the example, we use the TEI prefix mechanism, which is then expanded via the
          <gi>prefixDef</gi> element in the TEI header to resolve into a URI pointer (as
          explained in Section on <ref target="#sec-idents">Identifiers and referencing</ref>),
          most likely to pointing to <gi>taxonomy</gi> categories that give the definitions of
          the relations. A further point to notice is that the sentence serves as the Root
          element of the sentence, i.e. the fifth link of the UD analysis ties together the
          sentence with the top-most token of the sentence.</p>
        </div>
        
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-multimedia">
        <head>Multimedia</head>
        
        <p>Some corpora can also have data from other modalities associated with the transcripts,
        in particular audio or video recordings, and the facsimile of the original texts,
        particularly relevant for corpora of historcial texts. This section explains how to encode
        such data in the TEI encoded documents, where it is assumed that the actual speech, video
        and images are stored in separate files, and the TEI document makes reference to them.</p>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-speechvideo">
          <head>Speech and video</head>
          
          <p>The (speech) corpus can refer to and align with external audio and video data using
          the <gi>timeline</gi> element, explained in the Section on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SASYMP">Placing
          Synchronous Events in Time</ref> of the TEI Guidelines, and further elaborated in <ref
          target="https://www.iso.org/standard/37338.html">ISO 24624:2016 Language resource
          management -- Transcription of spoken language</ref>. While the ISO standard is better
          elaborated, it also changes and adds element definitions, so we are using the standard
          TEI variant of speech encoding as far as the schema is concerned, while taking into
          account, as much as possible, specific encoding choices as proposed by the ISO
          standard.</p>
          
          <p>First, TEI offers the <gi>recordingStmt</gi> element (a part of <gi>fileDesc</gi>
          of the TEI header) which contains the information about the recording(s) of the
          transcription. This information can be unstructured (i.e. a series of <gi>ab</gi>
          elements) or structured (contained in the <gi>recording</gi> element); CLARIN.SI
          recommends the structured version. As shown in the example below, the element
          contains information of the type of recording (audio / video), its duration<note>The
          <att>dur</att> values should follow the <ref
          target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-xmlschema-2-20041028/#duration">W3C
          datatype</ref>.</note> and a pointer to the file, possibly a responsibility statement
          (<gi>respStmt</gi>) of the person or agency that made the recording, the date when
          the recording file was made and the equipment used:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-recordingStmt">
            <recordingStmt>
              <recording type="audio" dur="PT43M45S">
                <media mimeType="audio/wav" url="WAV/Session_2018-12-01a.wav"/>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp>Audio capture</resp>
                  <name>John Dury</name>
                </respStmt>
                <time>2016-04-15</time>
                <equipment>
                  <ab>Video downloaded from U.K. parliament site.</ab>
                  <ab>Audio extracted from video with Audacity 1.4</ab>
                </equipment>
              </recording>
            </recordingStmt>
          </egXML>
          </p>
          
          <p>The mapping of time intervals of the recording to IDs in the TEI document is
          encoded in the <gi>timeline</gi> element, in particular in the contained
          <gi>when</gi> elements. As explained below, these IDs are then used to link elements
          in the transcription to the timeline, therefore each <gi>when</gi> element must have
          the <att>xml:id</att> attribute. The <gi>when</gi> elements must also be in the same
          order as the time-points they encode.</p>
          
          <p>As the example below shows, the timeline gives the unit in which the intervals are
          specified (typically second, <code>s</code>) and the time origin of the timeline,
          here referring to the first <gi>when</gi> element, at the very start of the
          recording, so specified with the absolute time.  Further <gi>when</gi> elements give
          the interval between this origin point and their end:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-timeline">
            <timeline unit="s" origin="#T0">
              <when xml:id="T0" absolute="00:00:00.0"/>
              <when xml:id="T1" interval="1.13" since="#T0"/>
              <when xml:id="T2" interval="3.84" since="#T0"/>
              <when xml:id="T3" interval="5.33" since="#T0"/>
              <when xml:id="T4" interval="9.35" since="#T0"/>
              <when xml:id="T5" interval="12.62" since="#T0"/>
            </timeline>
          </egXML>
          </p>
          
          <p>The IDs of the timeline synchronisation are then used by the <gi>u</gi>
	  elements in the transcription via their <att>start</att> and
          <att>end</att> attributes. In the examples below we give three cases of such linking:
          the first one gives a straightforward temporal structure on the <gi>u</gi>;
	  the second one uses the
          empty <gi>anchor</gi> element to give additional temporal structure for cases where
          the synchronised parts of the utterance are not further marked-up
	  (or the synchronisation is required for elements that don't have the <att>start</att> and
          <att>end</att> attributes); while the third and
          fourth demonstrate the case where two utterances are partially overlapping:<note>Note
          that in such cases we would also use the <att>prev</att> and <att>next</att>
          attributes, as shown in the <ref target="#exa-splitu">Example on split
          utterances</ref>.</note>:
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-utiming">
            <u who="#SPK0" start="#T0" end="#T1" xml:id="u2">Good morning!</u>
            <u who="#SPK1" start="#T1" end="#T3">Good morning, <anchor synch="#T2"/>Mr. president!</u>
            <u who="#SPK0" start="#T4" end="#T7">You do not have the <anchor synch="#T5"/>floor!</u>
            <u who="#SPK1" start="#T5" end="#T6">Sorry, <anchor synch="#T2"/>mate!</u>
          </egXML>
          </p>
        </div>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-facsimile">
          <head>Facsimile</head>
          <p>Especially for older text, where the exact appearance of the original is of interest,
          it can be advantageous to also enable viewing the facsimile together with the
          text transcription. How to achieve this in general is explained in the <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html">Chapter on
          Representation of Primary Sources</ref> of the TEI Guidelines.</p>
          
          <p>The simplest but also the most limiting way to achieve this is to have per-page
          facsimile files and use the page break i.e. <gi>pb</gi> element to mark page
          boundaries in the transcript and then directly specify the image file of the page
          with the <att>facs</att> attribute, as illustrated in the example below:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-pb">
            <body>
              <pb facs="PNG/page1.png"/>
              <!-- text contained on page 1 encoded here -->
              <pb facs="PNG/page2.png"/>
              <!-- text contained on page 2 encoded here -->
            </body>
          </egXML>
          </p>
          
          <p>By convention, this encoding indicates that the image indicated by the <att>facs</att>
          attribute represents the whole of the text following the <gi>pb</gi> element, up
          to the next <gi>pb</gi> element.</p>
          
          <p>A more complicated solution, where it is possible to have several images per page
          (e.g. in different resolutions) or to specify areas of a page is enabled by the
          <gi>facsimile</gi> element, which should appear immediately before the <gi>text</gi>
          element of a TEI document. The example below refers to the first and third pages
          directly with the <gi>graphic</gi> element, whereas the second page is encoded as a
          <gi>surface</gi> which then contains the page image in two resolutions:
          
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="exa-facsimile">
            <facsimile>
              <graphic xml:id="page1" url="PNG/page1.png"/>
              <surface xml:id="page2">
                <graphic type="600dpi" url="PNG/page2-highRes.png"/>
                <graphic type="300dpi" url="PNG/page2-lowRes.png"/>
              </surface>
              <graphic xml:id="page3" url="PNG/page3.png"/>
            </facsimile>
          </egXML>
          </p>
          
          <p>More complicated cases, such as delimiting portions of a page are also supported
          by the TEI Guidelines, and for these the reader is referred directly to the Section
          on <ref
          target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHFAX">Digital
          Facsimiles</ref>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-conversion">
        <head>Conversions</head>
        <p>A TEI encoded document is, in general, not meant to be used directly by software
        programs, rather it serves as an interchange and storage format.  Furthermore, most TEI
        documents are not "born TEI", but rather converted into TEI from some source format.
        In this section we discuss some up- and down-conversion scripts that have already been
        developed for transforming source formats into CLARIN.SI and from CLARIN.SI into
        formats immediately usable by software and are available in the Git repository of
        CLARIN.SI.</p>
        
        <div xml:id="sec-conllu">
          <head>Conversion from CoNLL-U</head>
          <p>To do!</p>
	</div>
      </div>
      
      <div xml:id="sec-ack">
        <head>Acknowledgements</head>
        
        <p>This proposal was inspired by a number of related projects, in
        particular: <ref target="https://tei-c.org/extra/teiinlibraries/">Best Practices for
        TEI in Libraries</ref>, the DARIAH and ELEXIS funded initiative <ref
        target="https://dariah-eric.github.io/lexicalresources/pages/TEILex0/TEILex0.html">TEI
        Lex0</ref> to develop an interchange encoding for machine readable dictionaries, and
        the <ref target="https://www.distant-reading.net/eltec/">ELTeC corpus</ref> initiative
        by the COST Action CA16204 <q>Distant Reading for European Literary History</q>.</p>
        
        <p>The work on these recommendations was funded by the <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/">CLARIN</ref>
        Research Infrastructure for Language Resources and Tools.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <divGen type="subtoc"/>
      <div xml:id="examplar">
        <head>Example document</head>
        <p>This section gives a complete example document and
	aims to illustrate the encoding of various aspects of corpus annotation.</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	       xml:id="exa-exemplar">
	  <!-- Does not render correctly! -->
          <xi:include href="tei_clarin_example.xml"/>
        </egXML>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="schema">
        <head>Formal specification</head>
	<schemaSpec ident="tei_clarin" start="TEI teiCorpus" docLang="en" prefix="tei_" xml:lang="en">
          <moduleRef key="core" except="binaryObject gb"/>
          <moduleRef key="tei" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="header" except="handNote typeNote scriptNote"/>
          <moduleRef key="textstructure"
		     except="argument div1 div2 div3 div4 div5 div6 div7 epigraph floatingText"/>
          <moduleRef key="corpus" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="transcr" except="am"/>
          <moduleRef key="figures" except=""/>
          <!-- Dictionaries no longer supported (will be when documentation is written - or merged with
	       TEILex0
	       moduleRef key="dictionaries" except=""/-->
          <moduleRef key="spoken" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="namesdates" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="linking" except=""/>
          <moduleRef key="analysis" except="interp interpGrp"/>
          <moduleRef key="iso-fs" except="bicond cond fsConstraints fsdLink if iff then vMerge vNot"/>
          <moduleRef key="gaiji" except=""/>
	</schemaSpec>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
